I would expect that people will try to
poison agents. Just remember, it's not a
matter of
if you'll get hacked.
It's only when and how often. Human
beings are the the weakest link.
The moment you connect Open Cloud to
your actual data,
an attacker [music]
can easily discover a vulnerability to
get to your data.
Well, I'm super excited to have Enrique
Salem here. He is a former CEO of
Symantec, uh leading the company to
being a billion-dollar powerhouse in the
security space, tens of thousands of
employees. He's now an investor at Bain
Capital Ventures, where he has invested
in Crusoe, uh Redis,
board of Docker, DocuSign, and a bunch
of other companies. So, it's great to
have you here. Really good to be here.
You were leading Brightmail, which was
the world's leading anti-spam company,
and you testified before the US Senate
about the spam crisis.
>> Yeah. You talked about your 7-year-old
daughter receiving all explicit spam,
and there was nothing that you as the
CEO of this company could do about it.
How How did you operate that company
internally knowing that you were
fighting this uphill battle? Yeah, it
it's so By the way, that the person
asking number of the questions back then
was Senator John McCain, which was which
was really fascinating. And and he I
I'll never forget, he asked me a really
important question. He said,
you know, we we can pass laws to try and
protect people. And
um I said, yeah, I get that. And and
then he said, the question is, how do we
have attribution? How do we determine
who sent it?
So that we know who to go after. And
that was the exact right question. And
so, what I was referencing was this idea
that uh
even if you see the spam
trying to figure out how to prevent it
from getting generated was very hard. We
could do things to block it.
But the creation part is more of like a
societal Exactly. It was a It was
exactly that, and it can come from
anywhere where there was no way to
actually uh
say, okay, well, if that's coming from,
you know, Southeast Asia,
we can somehow go after the person who
created it. So, the only thing we could
do was really try to prevent it from
getting to my daughter's computer.
So, that was the thing that we needed to
work on, not laws. So, laws The point
The point of the the message really was
laws weren't the solution to the
problem. Yeah, laws could not
disincentivize the behavior. Exactly.
Has uh has that changed over time? And
is there a way to stop it at the root?
It It's Again, it's it's a
jurisdictional problem. I mean, it
You can't Even if you could identify the
source, like a lot of uh sites that are
used to attack companies, they're not
hosted here in the US. Yeah. And you,
you know, they'll be hosted on some
small uh internet provider in some place
that our laws and even through other
relationships can't do much about. And I
imagine the imagine the spam problem is
exponentially worse now with AI agents.
What What's happened What's happening
now is where before we used to have to
hand-curate to create a very accurate
message, there's so much information
about people that now You can really
personalize it. Exactly. You can
personalize it in a way that
and we used to we used to do this to
show boards of directors how easy it was
to compromise a company, and we'd
basically show them we'd go we'd do a
little bit of research, and then we'd
walk in and say, watch, this is your
CTO, super talented person, he did a
presentation in South Korea, talked
about this topic. We're going to
generate We've generated this message,
and now you can easily have him read it
and go, oh, somebody's interested in the
presentation. Let me send it to him.
The reality is it's fraudulent, and what
you can do now is the level of work we
used to do to create that message can be
done instantaneously.
>> Instantaneously. And that's the scary
part. Enjoying the conversation? Got a
question? You can ask Enrique's digital
mind. You just check the link in the
comments or description. And so, is the
solution education where people should
be more skeptical of what they get, or
are you seeing solutions where you can
actually detect?
I think this I think you always want to
have some level of awareness and
understanding of what it could look
like, because you want people to be
alert.
>> Yeah. But it's not enough. You do need
solutions. You need the combination, the
awareness plus the the detection. The
The biggest challenge is always going to
be that I can create scenarios that you
may not respond to every time.
But as I create the scenario that says,
hey, you need to like classic one that
used to happen, two companies merge.
When the company The second company, the
acquired company, comes into the
company, sign up for your benefits.
The moment you're asked to sign up for
your benefits, if you receive a message
that says, click on this link,
sign up for your new benefits, you might
go, well, that seems situationally
accurate. I just got acquired, and I
should probably sign up for my benefits.
So, the trick is that
we'll never get No solution will ever be
foolproof to prevent anything from
getting to you.
>> You just have to adapt. You have to
adapt, you have to be vigilant, and
you have to pay attention. Um
And this is one of the biggest issues
with agents right now that I think
people are going to miss.
An agent can inherit your credentials,
your access.
But at some point security relies on
your judgment. Mhm. So, let me let me
give you an example. Um you know, I ran
a public company. I'd get the press
release for earnings
before earnings day. It would always
come into my inbox, you know, I'd go
through, I'd read it, try to understand
it, uh make sure that I agreed with what
it was saying. But imagine I have an
agent that its role is to promote things
that are relevant for the company. And
loud the headline in the press release
says um
record-breaking quarter.
So, my agent picks it up and says, let
me repost this. And influence the
algorithm. Yeah, that says, let me let
me repost post this on, you know, you
pick it. Um
and it reposts it, but it's before
earnings day.
Mhm. Our security team knows Enrique's
not going to post this.
But how do I tell my agent
to not use that
press release as something that should
be amplified?
So, that's where the subtle problem is
is that you don't have the the human
being at some point your security team
relies on you having some level of
judgment.
And so, that we need to be able to
control the judgment of agents. Exactly.
Now, think about think about how hard
that problem is.
>> Yeah, it seems like [laughter]
billions of dollars and things going to
that.
>> And and I think look, I I've probably
seen no exaggeration, dozens of
companies attacking different parts of
how do we observe agents, how do we
control the data, and there's some
interesting things out there. I still
think there's more innovation that has
to happen, because to the point we're
just making on the judgment, and it's
not there yet.
>> Mhm. And I think it's going to be still
quite a bit of time before we get to the
level of a security team being able to
say, I can trust agents to have the same
level of responsibility. Now, security
teams will try to put other controls in
place,
but remember, if I put so many controls
in place, at some point you say, I can't
do my job.
It It The The question's going to be
Yeah. when when humans are involved,
humans make decisions, and
unfortunately, when you have
um
any given day, you make tens, if not
hundreds, of decisions. I think when you
look at an agent where agents are making
these decisions, the question is, how do
I confuse the agent to do something? And
And you should expect this to happen.
You should expect that people will say,
I know that what people do is have a
uh agent that looks at your calendar
every day.
And then it prepares something for you.
I would expect that people will try to
poison agents to doing things like
schedule a meeting for Enrique to do
XYZ. And I'll go, oh, my assistant said
I have to go over here. And and and you
know, you just They'll I expect agents
to get poisoned. But I think what what I
what I mean by that ultimately is um
send,
you know, $100 to our, you know, we have
a uh a dog, to our dog sitter, you know,
and have me say, oh, yeah, you should do
that.
But it realized by looking at my
calendar that we're going out of town
this weekend, and so I should we do need
the dog sitter, and unfortunately, it
made it up and created an entry that I
said, oh, yeah, yeah, pay that.
So, that's what I'm worried about with
it.
>> And you you you trusted.
>> You trusted. You You trusted. And See,
the thing is,
if you understand context of my
calendar,
you now start having more ability to
tell an agent to take an action that I'm
going to say yes to.
That That's the thing that I I worry
about.
So, you've been watching cyber threats
since before many of us all of us here
were born. [laughter]
Um
does AI introduced
any new threats that were not possible
before, or is it just arming both sides
with more powerful weapons on the same
things, like
amplifying spam, for example?
I think you're I think you're amplifying
fishing significantly, and because
human beings are the the weakest link,
um in many ways, it really gives the
attacker an asymmetric advantage.
Meaning Meaning, we're going to use it
on the defensive side,
>> Yeah.
but attackers, at least today,
have the ability to use it in a way
that's so context-aware.
Social engineering. Social engineering,
context-aware, that it makes it
it makes it more difficult to to defend.
People have been saying something I
don't agree with, which is
it makes somebody who's not that
sophisticated be a good attacker.
I don't really agree with that because
what's happening is our defenses are
getting better, too.
What it is doing, though, it's arming
the folks who are really talented with
even better tools to attack. So, I I
don't think it's it it doesn't lower the
bar,
you know, for somebody who doesn't know
anything about attacking to suddenly be
great at it. Um it it really makes both
sides better, and the challenge is, you
know, when we see what we call the cyber
kill chain, which is how do you get into
a company? Mhm.
Um
usually you're either doing it through
social engineering or exploiting a
vulnerability.
What's happened, as we know in the
current news, is that it's easier and
easier to exploit vulnerabilities.
Now, the good news is we have companies
that are getting better and better at
protecting against vulnerabilities. So,
you know, I think it's always seeing how
do the good guys catch up?
I've always said that, you know,
attackers have a short-term
advantage cuz they're not worried about
how they use the technology.
>> No.
Right? They don't care.
>> E- Exactly. Exactly. They don't care.
>> easier to operate on. Exactly. And so,
but for the for the defenders, we
follow the rules.
>> the right way. Do it the right way, and
it takes a little longer, but but we
always get better. And if if all the
systems we'd built didn't exist, you
know, we just had a
everything was wide open and easily
compromised, I mean, it would be a very
different risk-risk prone
world, but the defenses get better. Is
that a never-ending race? Is there ever
a point where
maybe we have something that is adaptive
on its own?
You know, I I I always
want to be careful
that it's not for lack of imagination
that we say we can't do something. I I I
fear, though,
as long as there's an attacker who has
an interest, something to gain that they
care about,
um
with enough time, persistence,
potentially financial backing, it's hard
to say that you won't get compromised.
May take longer. Mhm. Maybe a little
harder.
But, so I think it's always going to be
this cat-and-mouse,
you know, continuing escalating
defenses, continuing to
escalating attackers. The The key is
that in software we usually have other
controls in place. So, just cuz you find
a vulnerability, there's tens of
thousands of vulnerabilities that are in
software and easily exploited. So, I
worry more about
things that we can't see. So, you know,
we talk about
models have weights.
And I worry more about models getting
poisoned
than I worry about people exploiting
vulnerabilities. And I And I think that
you know, this whole mythos discussion,
um
Anthropic has a new model that they're
talking about that creates all kinds of
power for attacking, in effect. Um
I worry more about model poisoning
than I worry about vulnerabilities
because I think we'll be really good at
figuring out how to
uh control the blast radius of any one
bomb. If you could describe
the nightmare scenario of
shadow AI, as you've called it this
year, that hasn't happened yet. What
does that look like?
I think the the nightmare scenario is,
you know, agents
that
start saying, "I'm trying to do what you
asked me to do,
but don't have enough context." And they
start publishing information that you
don't want out there. That is That is
the The nightmare scenario is that the
agents
uh overlook access control completely
and just start taking things and saying,
"I'm doing the right thing. I'm doing
the right thing."
And in that scenario,
>> giving the information for an objective.
>> Exactly.
>> Okay. Exactly. And And I And I think
that
what I worry about is
right now everybody is trying to say,
"How do I use AI in a productive way?"
But sometimes to do that, I need access
to your email.
I need access to your Slack or Teams or
whatever.
And I might say I'm going to give my,
you know, Hermes agent access to all of
this data and bypass what my IT team
thinks. But now you've basically opened
up the crown jewels
to this agent who may inadvertently do
something you don't want. And so, the
nightmare scenario is it's just
publishing everything
and doing it in the name of trying to
help you. And I don't I haven't bought
into these whole black agents
blackmailing you. I I I don't know that
I quite
if it suddenly gets, and I've read all
about them, that says, "Hey, I I think
that
you're preventing me from doing my job,
so now I'm going to do something that
gets you to let me gives me access or
control." I'm not sure I buy that yet.
>> Okay. I'm not sure I buy it.
>> yet. I'm not there yet. And And the
reason I'm not there yet is because
at the end of the day,
I, as the person running the agent, can
shut it off.
So, if it if you were to black Let's say
my agent was blackmailing me,
I'd be like,
"Delete."
>> [laughter]
>> Unless it's an agent of an agent. Yeah,
I mean,
>> And you you've lost [clears throat]
control at that point. Well, I think I
think the question will be is you're
asking
does the agent get into a position where
I'm not really in control of it? Now, I
think that starts getting to a scary
scenario. Yeah.
Where
I tell something to do something on my
behalf, but I don't have a way of
turning it off. Okay.
That could That could That could start
leading down that path. Yeah, let's hope
we don't get there. Uh on the first
nightmare scenario that you brought up,
is the solution to just lead with
caution right now on, you know, maybe
don't connect Open Claw to your Gmail?
Well, I mean, I think I think the What I
always try to say is
figure out the tool you can use that you
have confidence in.
So,
I wouldn't start by saying, "Let me
give" That's why we're putting it
Everybody says use it on a Mac Mini,
right? Don't put it on your main
computer. But But part of that reason is
if you were to prior to any of the new
things we've uncovered,
if you're running a piece of software
that has access to everything you have,
it Remember our Stuxnet story? If we can
compromise systems that are that
protected, we can compromise Open Claw.
So, the real issue is the moment you
connect Open Claw to your actual data,
an attacker
can easily discover a vulnerability to
get to your data.
So, that's
So, yeah, so that's the problem. The
problem is not
what Open Claw can do. The problem is
Open Claw is somewhat
able to access it and may do things you
don't want, but then also that I, as an
attacker,
can compromise Open Claw. Is that why
you haven't set up Open Claw yet?
>> I have not set up Open Claw on my main
computer. What would have to be true?
I'd have to feel confident that I knew
how to control what it would do from an
data access
and other activities. We are working on
similar things, though, right? So, as an
industry, we're finding,
I would say, uh trusted
versions, you know, Perplexity AI
computer,
you know, as an example of same kind of
technology that gives it access to many
of the things I want,
but without necessarily taking on the
same risks.
>> What makes you trust Perplexity AI
computer? Is it their brand? Is it evals
that you've been given? Cuz I feel like
trust is almost like a very subjective
thing.
It is. Um I I think that
reputationally,
whether it be any any company today, the
risks are too high. Like we've seen some
public headlines, right, of people
fictitiously making up reports. Yeah.
Right? And so then And And those
companies, I mean, venture capitalists
aren't going to trust
consumers and customers aren't going to
trust them. And so, why do I trust
someone like a Perplexity or, you know,
I would say it's because they have too
much to lose.
>> Mhm.
And I'm not a believer that when you're
doing something wrong, you can keep it a
secret forever. Yeah, you can count on
incentives and human nature. Right?
>> Yeah. Somebody's going to say, "Wait,
this is wrong."
And they will
>> Yeah, that scale of a company. Right?
So, you you
you at some point you start saying,
does the reputation and trust the
people's trust in this company matter?
Yeah. So, recently in the last month, a
lot of known AI startups and com- big
companies have had major breaches. Yes.
Um
Anthropic, Mistral,
what does this tell you about the
current state of startups as part one of
the question? Then part two of the
question is if this is something that
will continue, you think data as a moat
will
can sustain itself given that data can
be hacked?
Yeah, there's a couple parts to that.
So, the first part is
um
I remember when I many years ago working
with the Department of Homeland
Security, and
uh Andy Purdy, he was uh
deputy secretary, he said to me,
"Just remember, it's not a matter of
if you'll get hacked.
It's only when and how often."
And so, if you have something of value,
you're a target.
And so, you you have to to
that if that's what's going on, these
companies you mentioned all companies
that are trying to innovate
a lot of value at the forefront.
And so they're going to be bigger and
bigger targets.
And and so what you have to do is you
have to say to yourself
if I like when I ran Symantec, you know,
Fortune 500 company, I would have told
our security team
what are the things we have to care
about because if it got out and got onto
the front page of, you know, the paper
it would be so damaging to us.
And you got to have that mindset. Um is
this world ever going to be
uh so secure that
you don't have to worry about these
attacks? Absolutely not.
Absolutely not.
No one's safe. No one is safe. With that
in mind as an investor, do you do you
believe in data motes being a sustaining
uh advantage for startups if like
especially in this day and age the more
valuable data you get you're going to
have more attackers.
Yeah, look
I think that
data can be
a moat
but not on its own.
See, I I I always try to when I work
with entrepreneurs, I try and spend time
on what are all the things that have to
be true for us to build a really
successful company. And when I listen to
a pitch a lot of times people will like
VCs have told us to prepare for what's
the moat, what's defensible, what's our
advantage. And I can tell the difference
when somebody tries to say I have an
advantage cuz I have some set of set of
data, I have contracts, I have
something. But if they can't put the
whole thing together
of why that matters
that's not good enough.
Right? And so I I tell people, you know
you can articulate a story why data
matters
but do you want me to believe that no
one will ever be able to get
access to similar data
for the life of my investment as an
early stage investor? Yeah, with your
perspective I think. You have to have a
7 to 10 years, right? So how how how are
we going to keep this? And so it's
really I I I find that
it's always a a combination of really
important things
and
it's not
I've never seen very few companies I
should say there that are really built
on
one thing that has really made them
successful.
Right? It's usually a combination of
fact it's a combination of important
factors.
So data motes it's an interesting thing
to talk about
probably in some cases necessary but not
sufficient. I like it. Some contrarian
takes in this talk. You have this three
eyes framework for
founders building in
security infrastructure. Can you tell me
a bit about that framework and
which of those three eyes do people
sacrifice that ends up being the biggest
mistake most of the time?
Yeah, so the three eyes are really when
you're building a security product, you
want to think about it being
invincible, invisible, and inexpensive.
And and invincible means
uh secure enough for what you're trying
to do. Everything doesn't have to be
kept at the same level of security. A
national security system is probably
needs a different level of security
than, you know, a marketing document
that I'm working on.
So invincible is fit for purpose.
Um
invisible is that the users
it's not being intrusive so that they
want to turn it off.
Right? Because if it's so intrusive
you're like, how do I get around this
thing because I can't do my job.
And the third one we say inexpensive,
inexpensive isn't just the cost of
buying the software, it's the operating
of the software. How many people have to
be involved? The one that I see
often times be missed is the third one
because you come up with a great idea
and then you say, well, I'm going to get
companies to use it.
But then what ends up happening is they
forget that it still has to be operated.
It has to like if it's throwing off a
bunch of alerts and saying, hey, here's
a problem, here's a problem, here's a
problem. Someone actually has to take an
action. Exactly. And so operationally
the third eye
of inexpensive, which is the cost of
software and the operational side
and the time. Exactly is the one that I
think sometimes gets overlooked. And you
know, one of your one of your previous
uh
uh discussions was with a gentleman who
really focused on design.
And and I think sometimes design
gets overlooked by folks who use your
experience people don't really think
about it with security because they're
it's very different.
>> Exactly. So that that's the key that's
the key. So you've seen the most
successful security companies are user
experience first. With.
Yeah.
>> I would tell you a soft, you know,
he built two companies his his first one
great user experience sold it to
Microsoft and the second one obviously
sold to Google.
Um so I think user experience products
you know, um like Notion, you know,
Linear. I mean these are great products.
Totally.
You gave a talk at Dartmouth called the
fog of war
where you talked about making decisions
under radical uncertainty and
I feel right now we have so much
uncertainty. You know, the models are
getting better, there are more risks,
Anthropic had this model that they're
not releasing.
How are you approaching making decisions
under such uncertainty as an investor
as, you know, especially like things can
be vibe coded and not really sure where
motes are. And then how do you also
advise founders on how to approach this
kind of new era of uncertainty?
I I think you have to be able to make
decisions and you you'll you'll end up
in paralysis if you feel like
I have to know everything about it
before I can make a decision. And and
the framework that I've always liked,
which was, you know, I can't take credit
for it, you know, Amazon famously had
their one-way doors.
And and I think there are very few
one-way doors and you have to be
comfortable with that. I I I think if
you're making decisions today
what are the things you're saying that
in
you know, some small period of time you
couldn't correct. And so so I think of
it that way, which is there's very few
decisions that can't easily be undone.
But if you don't make the decisions,
you're falling behind. Yeah.
I'm seeing a theme across a lot of your
answers. It's really it's not about
prevention, it's prioritization. It's
about finding those top things. Exactly.
And and the things that
that if you get right give you a lot of
upside and if you you don't you can fix.
Yeah.
Um something that we ask every person
who comes to the office is what is your
greatest hardship that you've had to
overcome in your life. I think I know
the answer after researching you but I'm
curious
uh what your answer is. You know, I I
would I I think that it's interesting.
You'd be surprised um
you know, my father got Parkinson's when
he was 69.
I think that was probably the toughest
period of my life. You know, somebody,
you know, I I've I've been very blessed
with fabulous family and parents.
Um you know, I tell people I won the
lottery with my parents. You know, when
my dad got sick and I couldn't do
anything about it, that was really hard.
That was and and and
feeling helpless, you know, it's like I
when
you know, I'm an immigrant. I
you know, fight back, you know, I you
know, I've got a lot of resilience but
feeling helplessness Yeah. is pretty
tough.
>> Just where you're an high agency person.
Yeah, that's tough. That's tough. And
you know, as I saw, you know, the
unfortunate and he had a very variant
Parkinson's called Lewy body dementia
but when
um you just see somebody you love
deteriorating
and feel powerless that was really
tough. That was really tough. Well,
appreciate you sharing that.
I was I was going to say something much
more
business like when when you
left Symantec.
>> Yeah. Um but I'm sure that was hard for
a different reason. Well, you know what
was interesting about about the my my
exit from Symantec in 2012 was the board
and I
didn't see eye to eye on a number of
things. And one of the things that I
always believed even early on, maybe
it's touch of arrogance,
was I was never afraid of losing my job.
So I was always going to tell people
what I think. And one of the things that
>> Why is that? Cuz I always felt I could
get a new job. Nice.
Right? I mean it's like, you know, I I
had a skill. I mean I was a software
developer and I knew I could always
well, today today I can't write code
probably [laughter] as
good code. But but I always felt that
you you have to be willing to tell
people what you really think. And you
know, the debate with the Symantec board
was always about what's going to lead us
to be more successful. And I felt we
have to keep investing in innovation. We
have to, you know, if you're if you're
cutting costs
and you're not focused on what's going
to make you relevant
then at some point you're out of
business.
And that was the debate cuz I wanted to
lean into some ideas that we had and
they were like, no, we should be more
mindful of the bottom line and I'm like,
you know, this isn't going to work. And
so ultimately that led to, you know,
them asking me to to leave and you know,
while that was not a happy day
um one thing that mattered was when the
press release went out the next morning
um
number of my friends, one in particular,
said, hey, you know, if you want a place
to work, um got an office for you, you
know, show up and
and so I just felt like, you know, quite
frankly
uh
a lot of people around me felt like, you
know, we want to work with Enrique
again. Yeah, you were good no matter
what. Exactly. In the remainder of 2026,
what kind of opportunities, ideas,
founders do you want to attract into
your life this year?
Yeah, look, I think the world is
changing a lot and
you know, I look at it and you know, we
talk a lot about this idea of
we're seeing the first wave of what's
possible through AI. Uh
we haven't yet seen the next wave. And I
I do believe there's going to be a whole
set of new ideas around even some of the
things you and I have talked about where
I want to understand people and how they
think way better. Mhm.
And and and that idea is super helpful.
You know, I I tried to always understand
the human being.
And that's what I think over time we'll
be a better at understanding people.
Um what's going to happen big though
that's different, not conventional
thinking?
Yeah, I think that we're seeing a big
change, which is
software has value
and will always have value how we build
it and so forth.
But we're seeing other areas and so I'm
spending a lot of time in
um
things that you would say are more in
the physical world. So, you know, we're
building data centers at Crusoe. We're
you know, what does it mean for power?
What does it mean for uh new forms of
silicon, interconnects, memory? Uh you
know, we have a big investment at Bain
Capital in in memory, which has done
incredibly well because there's such a
high demand. And so
it's not just about the things we've
historically invested in. So, I want to
see things that are potentially you
would say is is Enrique interested in
power generation?
Yeah, I am.
So, it's a whole set of new areas. Thank
you so much. This is great. Pleasure.
Amazing. Thanks for tuning in. If you
enjoyed today's episode and want
personalized advice from Enrique, head
to the link in the comments or
description to ask his digital mind on
Delphi.